原創翻譯  雙語字幕
最新連載海外影視劇下載
請登陸 www.YYeTs.com
僅供交流學習  禁止商用盈利
翻譯     秋乙一   刁萌   我有貓我驕傲   Margaery
翻譯     子V   鹽湖涼開水   秋明月
"那些老把加州享樂主義掛在嘴邊的人  一定沒見識過薩克拉門托的圣誕節"
瓊安·迪迪恩
翻譯     芝士   Murky   回風舞雪兮
校對     斯嘉麗會有學上的
時間軸    Great  吃土少女  JO鳥嘛  cci小白  壬虛浪影
你覺得我看起來像薩克拉門托人嗎
Do you think I look like I'm from Sacramento?
后期     8T
你就是薩克拉門托人
You are from Sacramento.
總監     somehacker   杏仁斯嘉麗
用不著你做  會有別人鋪平的
You don't have to do that.
保持整潔是好習慣
Well, it's nice to make things neat and clean.
-準備好回家了嗎  -準備好了
- You ready to go home? - Ready.
她將手放在他的頸后  撐著他的頭
Her hand moved behind his head and supported it.
手指溫柔地理著他的頭發
Her fingers moved gently in his hair.
她抬起頭  看向谷倉的另一頭
She looked up and across the barn,
然后她抿著嘴  神秘地微笑
and her lips came together and smiled mysteriously.
您正在收聽的是
You've been listening to...
《憤怒的葡萄》
...the Grapes of Wrath,
作者約翰·史坦貝克  如果您
by John Steinbeck. If you --
這趟大學之旅花了21小時5分鐘
Our college trip took 21 hours and five minutes.
等等  不用特地放東西聽了
Hey, wait. Let's just sit with what we heard.
-你是說真的嗎  -我們沒必要
- Are you serious? - Well, we don't have to constantly
一直自娛自樂  不是嗎
be entertaining ourselves, do we?
我希望我能經歷一些事情
I wish I could live through something.
-你沒經歷過嗎  -沒有
- Aren't you? - Nope.
2002年唯一亮點就是它正反讀都一樣
The only exciting thing about 2002 is that it's a palindrome.
好吧  你過得比誰都糟  所以你贏了
Okay, fine. Well, yours is the worst life of all, so you win.
-你生氣了  -我沒有  只是
- Oh, so now you're mad -- - No, it's just...
-就因為我想聽音樂嗎  -你這是無理取鬧
- Because I wanted to listen to music? - You're being ridiculous,
其實你過得還不錯
because you have a great life.
真是抱歉  我做不到十全十美
I'm sorry I'm not perfect.
沒人要求你要十全十美  你能體諒別人就行了
No one's asking you to be perfect. Just considerate would do.
反正我也不想在這個州讀大學
I don't even want to go to school in this state anyway.
我討厭加州  我想去東海岸
I hate California. I want to go to the east coast.
我和你爸爸只能勉強付得起本州的學費
Your dad and I will barely be able to afford in-state tuition.
-可以申請貸款  獎學金  -你哥哥那么聰明
- There are loans, scholarships. - Your very smart brother,
他連工作都找不到
he can't even find a job.
他和謝麗有工作
He and Shelly work. They have jobs.
他們在雜貨店打包  這算不上事業
They bag at the grocery store. That is not a career.
他們還上的伯克利
And they went to Berkeley.
你爸爸的公司到處都在裁人
Your father's company is laying off people right and left.
這你知道嗎  你當然不知道
Did you even know that? No, of course you don't,
因為你只會考慮自己
because you don't think about anybody but yourself.
能上圣心高中已經夠奢侈了
And Immaculate Heart is already a luxury.
圣心個屁  那是你的意愿  不是我的
Immaculate fart. You wanted that, not me.
在薩克拉門托高中  米格爾親眼看見有人被捅
Miguel saw someone knifed in front of him at Sac High.
你想去那兒嗎  你是說
Is that what you want? So, you're telling me
你想看別人在你面前捅人嗎
that you want to see somebody knifed right in front of you?
他根本就沒看到
He barely saw that.
我只是想去有文化氛圍的地方
I wanna go where culture is,
比如紐約  或者至少去康涅狄格
like New York, or at least Connecticut...
我怎么養了你這么個自命高雅的人
How in the world did I raise such a snob?
或者新罕布什爾  作家都住在樹林里
...or New Hampshire, where writers live in the woods.
反正那兒的學校你也進不去
You couldn't get into those schools, anyway.
-媽媽  -你連駕照都考不過
- Mom! - You can't even pass your driver's test.
那是因為你不讓我好好練習
Because you wouldn't let me practice enough!
不管你努不努力  用不用心  都也就那樣
The way that you work, or the way that you don't work,
你連州內學校的學費都不值  克里斯汀
you're not even worth state tuition, Christine.
我的名字是淑女鳥
My name is Lady Bird.
其實那不是你名字
Well, actually, it's not,
-它太滑稽了  -叫我淑女鳥
- and it's ridiculous -- - Call me Lady Bird.
-你名字是克里斯汀  -你保證過會那樣叫我的
- Because your name is Christine. - Like you said you would.
你就該去市立學院
You should just go to city college.
就你那套工作的德行
You know, with your work ethic,
就該去市立學院  然后進監獄
just go to city college, and then to jail,
再回市立學院上課
and then back to city college,
然后你可能就懂得要怎么振作起來
and then maybe you'd learn to pull yourself up
而不是老指望別人會怎么樣
and not expect everybody to --
去你的吧  老媽
以圣父之名
In the name of the father,
以圣子圣靈之名
and the son, and the holy spirit.
阿門
Amen.
-愿主與你同在  -也愿主與你同在
- Let the lord be with you. - And also with you.
歡迎大家
I want to welcome all of you
返校參加新學年的學習
back to the start of the new school year,
淑女鳥
澤維爾高中的男孩們  圣心高中的女孩們
all the Xavier boys and Immaculate Heart girls.
萬福圣母瑪利亞  你充滿圣寵
Hail Mary, full of grace.
主與你同在
The lord is with thee.
你在婦女中是有福的
Blessed art thou amongst women...
榮譽歸于您  我的主
Glory to you, o lord.
我謹宣誓效忠
I pledge allegiance to the flag
美利堅合眾國國旗
of the United States of America,
及效忠其所代表之共和國
and to the Republic for which it stands,
上帝保佑的  團結一致的
one nation under god, indivisible,
永遠銘記911
自由平等全民皆享的國度
with Liberty and justice for all.
投給阿曼達  就是投給男孩們
A vote for Amanda is a vote for boys,
以及健康食品的自動販賣機
boys and healthy vending machines,
沒人想吃高卡路里的瑪芬
because no one wants a muffin with that many calories.
別問我
Do not ask me,
"布魯諾老師  期末考試會不會考這個"
"Mr. Bruno, is this gonna be on the finals,"
歡迎返校
"布魯諾老師  期中考試會不會考這個"
or, "Mr. Bruno, is this gonna be on the midterm?"
因為我不會告訴你的
Because I'm not gonna tell you.
這不是你們該關心的事
That is none of your business.
沒規定說要告訴你們  這里我做主
Those aren't the rules. This is my house.
《圣約翰書信》選讀
"A reading from a letter of St. John."
我們害怕自己逃不出過往
We're afraid that we will never escape our past,
害怕不可知的未來
and we're afraid of what the future will bring.
害怕去不了心儀的學校
We're afraid that we will not get into the college of our choice.
害怕得不到別人的愛
We're afraid we won't be loved,
不被喜歡  無法成功
we won't be liked, we won't succeed.
這些都是經典  圣奧古斯丁[古羅馬天主教思想家]
Here are the classics -- St. Augustine, of course,
高級神學
阿奎納[經院哲學家]  還有我最欣賞的克爾凱郭爾[丹麥神學家]
Aquinas, my favorite, Kierkegaard --
他的愛情故事才是重頭戲
Oh, wait until you hear his love story.
絕對讓你神魂顛倒
It will make you swoon.
來看第二個話題  全球化的威脅
El segundo tema, de los desafíos globales.
救世主耶穌基督降臨
And the coming of our savior, Jesus Christ.
天下萬國  普世權威
For the kingdom, the power,
一切榮耀  永歸于你
and the glory are yours, now and forever.
阿門
Amen.
你的海報讓一些同學不太舒服
Some of the students were disturbed by your posters.
給淑女鳥投票  淑女鳥要當主席
只是鳥頭加女生身體而已
It's just a bird head on a lady body,
或者女生頭加鳥身體
or vice versa.
我覺得這些圖有些令人不安
I think it's a little upsetting.
競選是我的傳統
It's my tradition to run for office.
但別擔心  我選不上的
Don't worry. I won't win.
我擔心的不是這個
That's not what I'm worried about.
這件事不會影響我的獎學金  對吧
This won't mess with my scholarship, will it?
不會  你獎學金沒問題
No. You're okay there.
我認為你的表現欲很強
You have a performative streak, I think.
我也這么想
Yeah, I think that too.
或許你會喜歡戲劇
Maybe you would enjoy theater arts.
秋季音樂劇正在面試招演員
They're having auditions for the fall musical.
我們這兒也有音樂劇嗎
Do we have that here?
我們和澤維爾高中的男生們聯合排演
It's a collaborative effort with the men at Xavier.
為什么我都高三了才第一次聽說
How am I a senior and not know we have that?
或許是因為你沒有積極參加社區活動
Perhaps you haven't always been an active part of this community.
秋季排演音樂劇  春季則是話劇
They do a fall musical and a spring play,
我聽說場場爆滿
and from what I hear, it's a real blast.
我想去參加奧數比賽培訓
What I'd really like is to be on math olympiad.
但你不是特別擅長數學
But math isn't something you're terribly strong in.
這倒是
That we know of yet.
克里斯汀  "淑女鳥"
-給你  -謝謝
- There you go. - Thanks.
朱莉安  "朱莉"
"朱莉"不需要用引號
"Julie" doesn't need to be in quotes.
-但這不是我真名  -這和我的不一樣
- But it's not my real name. - It's not the same thing.
好像不是吧
I'm not sure you're right.
我喜歡這個街區
I love this neighborhood.
對  太美了
Yeah, it's so beautiful.
要是我住這兒
If I lived here,
我絕對要在家后院辦婚禮
I would definitely have my wedding in the backyard.
我會每天都請朋友來家里寫作業  吃零食
I'd have friends over all the time to study and eat snacks.
我還會說
I'd be like,
"媽  我們拿零食上樓  去電視房吃了"
"Mom, we're taking the snacks upstairs to the TV room."
我會有自己的浴室
I'd have my own bathroom.
我不能阻止你們倆混蛋在這兒玩
I can't stop you dicks from hanging out here,
但你們別把雜志弄皺了
but quit wrinkling all the magazines!
只要我進店  我就不是你妹妹
When I'm in this store, I'm not your sister.
我是顧客  米格爾  顧客總是對的
I'm a customer, Miguel. I'm always right.
從她搬進來后
Ever since she moved in,
你哥哥和謝麗就差不多合體了
your brother and Shelly are becoming the same person.
別胡說
No way.
好吧  可能確實如此
Yeah, okay. Maybe.
看見沒  為什么我就不能長她這樣
See, why don't I look like that?
哪怕一次就好
Yeah. Just once,
我希望能在聽《紐約節奏》的時候
I'd like to have the song "New York Groove" playing
覺得這首歌寫的就是我的生活
and feel like it really applies to my life.
你從沒去過紐約
You've never even been to New York.
這就是為什么我想申請紐約的大學
That's why I'm applying to New York colleges.
你知道莎拉·勞倫斯學院就住在紐約嗎
Do you know if Sarah Lawrence is actually in the city?
你父母給你出錢上學
Your parents would pay for that?
有獎學金  助學金
Scholarships, financial aid...
我會找到辦法的
I'll figure it out.
我媽覺得沒學校會要我  但她大錯特錯了
My mom thinks I can't get in, but she is sorely mistaken.
-恐怖襲擊怎么辦  -別來共和黨那一套
- What about terrorism? - Don't be a republican.
我很可能就去個市立學院
Probably just gonna go to city college.
把雜志放回去
Put the magazine back!
該死
Shit!
你還好嗎  媽媽
You doing okay, mama?
還好  太嚇人了  是不是
Yeah, that was terrifying, wasn't it?
還好有你在
Thank god you were there.
我們以后不能再用鉛筆了
So I guess we can't have pencils anymore.
是的  以后還是用蠟筆吧
Yeah, just gotta go back to quill tipped markers. Crayola.
好的  謝謝  送你的  我給寶寶買的
Right. Thank you. It's for you. I got it for the baby.
-我忍不住買了  -她喜歡粉色
- I couldn't resist it. - She loves pink.
說是給寶寶  其實主要是給安德里亞和你的
It's more for you and Andrea than it is for the baby.
對不起我沒來得及包得那么精美
I'm sorry I didn't have time to wrap it.
-沒事  這樣很好  -好吧
- No, it's perfect. - Okay. Good.
明天見  或者說  待會兒見
I'll see you tomorrow. Or, I mean, later.
-謝謝  -不用謝
- Thank you. - Okay.
你知不知道牙膏根本沒有用
Did you know toothpaste is basically ineffective.
-就像吃薄荷糖一樣  -邁克·凱利死了
- It's like sucking on a mint. - Mike Kelly died.
我根本不知道他又生病了
I didn't even know he was sick again.
他多大年紀了
How old was he?
才56歲
Only 56.
-我和謝麗能進來嗎  -等一下  孩子
- Can Shelly and I get in there? - In a minute, honey.
-我和爸爸還在里面  -那確實太年輕了
- Dad and I are still in here. - That's too young.
淑女鳥  你最好穿好衣服
Lady Bird, you better be dressed.
我穿好了
I am dressed.
我要寫張字條問候一下他們
Yeah. I'm gonna send them a note.
你覺得謝麗和米格爾
Do you think that Shelly and Miguel
會在沙發床上做嗎
have sex on the pullout couch?
當然會
Oh, yeah.
為什么不能讓我炒雞蛋
Why can't I just make the eggs?
因為你做得太慢
Because you take too long,
而且會弄得一團糟  我還得收拾殘局
you make a big mess, and I have to clean the whole thing up.
吃雞蛋不利于保護環境
Eggs aren't good for the environment anyways.
-什么  -你聽到了
- What? - You heard her.
麻煩你快點吃
Eat quickly, please.
看看這些照片
Look at all these pictures.
每家報紙看起來都跟《今日美國》一個樣
Every newspaper looks like USA Today.
謝麗和我在試著當素食主義者
Shelly and I are trying to be vegan,
所以我們開始喝豆奶
hence the soy milk.
你們穿的是皮夾克
You wear leather jackets.
是古著  不會促進皮質產業發展
But they're vintage, so they don't support the industry.
雞蛋還沒熟  還有白色的東西
They aren't done. There's white stuff.
你知道你有多愛布蘭博斯嗎
You know how much you love Brambles?
豬都比他聰明
Pigs are smarter than him even.
我從沒覺得布蘭博斯是個天才  好嗎
I never thought Brambles was a genius, okay?
媽媽  雞蛋都沒熟
Mom, the eggs are not done.
成  你自己炒該死的雞蛋
Fine. Make your own fucking eggs.
我本來就想  是你不讓我做的
I wanted to. You won't let me.
-你妹妹不喜歡我  -我餓了
- Your sister doesn't like me. - I'm hungry!
她喜歡你
She does.
現在你有機會了  我睡覺去了
You had your chance. Going to bed.
你知不知道艾拉妮絲·莫莉塞特
Did you know that Alanis Morissette
寫這首歌只用了十分鐘
wrote this song in only ten minutes?
我相信
I believe it.
我想申請幾個東海岸的學校
So, I'm applying to a couple east coast schools.
我想要你幫我申請助學金
I need you to help me with the financial aid applications,
但不能讓媽媽知道
but mom can't know.
我們...  學費不是很貴嗎
We... aren't they quite expensive?
第一  沒錯  所以才要申請助學金
First, yes. That's why financial aid.
第二  我得先被錄取
Second, I have to get in first.
你媽媽會不高興的
Mom won't be happy about it.
所以我得等到迫不得已再跟她吵
Which is why I don't want to fight about it before I have to.
-就停在這里吧  -你確定嗎
- Just pull over here. - Are you sure?
我可以送你到門口
I can drive you to the front.
不用  這里就好  我喜歡走路
No. This is fine. I like to walk.
我愛你
Well, I love you.
那我申請大學的事呢
So, what do you think about college?
-我會盡量幫你  -謝謝爸爸
- See what I can do. - Thanks, dad.
我也愛你  今天工作順利
I love you too. Have a good day at work.
滾石樂隊成員  與樂隊分分合合
我就像基斯·理查茲  不管在哪里都會開心的
I'm like Keith Richards. I'm just happy to be anywhere.
小妮子
Hey, bitch.
好了  女孩們
All right, girls.
-希望你們喜歡腌黃瓜  -謝謝馬特叔叔
- Hope you like pickles. - Thanks, Uncle Matt.
-真好  -他不是你叔叔
- Sweet. - He's not your uncle.
我就想這么叫  再見  媽媽
Just something I'm trying out. Bye, mom.
-再見  -愛你
- Bye. - Love you.
再見  我愛你
Bye. I love you.
-你媽媽真的愛你  -是的
- Your mom really likes you. - Yeah.
-我越來越胖了  -我也是
- I just keep getting fatter. - Me too.
-馬特很不錯  -是的
- Matt's awesome. - Yeah.
我希望他能跟我媽媽結婚  那就太好了
I hope he marries my mom. That would be so nice.
他答應等我十八歲的時候  把他那臺舊車給我
He promised me his old car when I turn 18.
那輛車應該是非法的
That car should be illegal.
詹娜·沃爾頓根本從來不開野路
Jenna Walton's not doing any off-roading.
去公園涼亭開什么越野車
She just goes to pavilions.
我聽說詹娜·沃爾頓家有一張美黑床
I heard Jenna Walton has a tanning bed in her house.
她真漂亮
She is so pretty.
她的皮膚閃閃發光
Her skin is luminous.
也許我們也應該試試美黑
Maybe we should try tanning.
是的
Yeah.
圣餐餅
僅由純小麥粉和純水制成
在浴缸里
...in the tub...
我把自己浸在水里  像現在這個姿勢
I scoot myself under, just like now, like this,
然后水就嘩啦啦
and then the water just-- whoop.
嘩啦啦
Schwoop.
你太惡心了
Ooh, you're so gross!
我可能三歲左右就會這么玩了
I think I figured it out when I was, like, three or something.
我用淋浴噴頭
I take the showerhead...
天吶
Oh, my god...
尷尬  我用的那個
Embarrassing, I use that.
我不知道我的那種方式對不對
I don't know if mine is the right kind though.
我猜跟里面真塞了根老二感覺不一樣
Maybe it's different when you actually have a penis in there.
也許會更爽一些
Like, it's more intense.
我覺得已經很爽了
Mine was pretty intense, I think.
你們不應該吃圣餅
You're not supposed to eat the wafers.
這些還沒行過圣禮
They're not consecrated.
*存活于世*
*Being alive.*
來吧  克里斯汀
Okay. Christine.
-是淑女鳥  -這是你的教名嗎
- Lady Bird. -Is that your given name?
-是的  -那為什么加了引號
- Yeah. - Why is it in quotes?
是我自己取的名字  我自己給自己取的
Well, I gave it to myself. It's given to me, by me.
好吧  開始吧  淑女鳥
Okay. Take it away, Lady Bird.
*每個人都說不要  每個人都說不要*
*Everybody says don't, everybody says don't.*
*每個人都說不要  說這是不對的*
*Everybody says don't, it isn't right.*
*不要  這樣是不好的*
*Don't, it isn't nice.*
*每個人都說不要  每個人都說不要*
*Everybody says don't, everybody says don't.*
*每個人都說不要踐踏草坪*
*Everybody says don't walk on the grass.*
*滾滾向前*
*Rolling along.*
*讓我帶給你安寧平靜*
*Make me a channel of your peace.*
*絕望之時我給你希望*
*Where there is despair in life, let me bring hope.*
*讓黑暗之處仍有光明*
*Where there is darkness, only light.*
*讓悲傷之地也有歡樂*
*And where there's sadness, ever joy.*
*天上住著巨人*
*There are giants in the sky.*
*天上住著高大威武又可怕的巨人*
*There are big, tall, terrible giants in the sky.*
*當你站在高處*
*When you're way up high and you look below*
*俯瞰這熟悉的世界*
*At the world you left and the things you know*
*即使是輕輕一瞥  你也知道*
*Little more than a glance ls enough to show you*
*自己有多渺小*
*Just how small you are.*
丹尼
你房里還有光  快點睡覺
I see light on in your room. Go to bed.
-恭喜你  -你也是  我們都被選上了
- Congratulations. - You too. We both got in.
所有來面試的都進了
Everyone who auditioned got in.
我的這個角色就跟沒選上一樣
The part I got was basically not getting in.
我都不知道我是怎么拿到這個角色的
I don't even know how I got cast in my part.
我也不懂
Me neither.
我才是那個特意穿了條裙子還準備了一首歌的人
I was the one who had a dress and prepared a song.
我知道
I know.
現在卻是你可以跟丹尼在臺上卿卿我我
Now you're gonna be all romantic with Danny on stage.
我可能就這么一次機會了  你明白嗎
It's probably my only shot at that, you know?
-你有筆嗎  -有
- Do you have a pen? - Yeah.
龍套/合唱  淑女鳥
-媽媽  -沒必要買這個
- Mom. - We don't need to buy that.
只要三美元  這周我太難熬了
It's only three dollars. I'm having a hard week.
如果你想看  可以去公立圖書館
Well, if you wanna read it, we can go down to the public library.
我想躺在床上看
I wanna read it in bed.
有錢人才那么干
That's something that rich people do.
我們沒錢
We're not rich people.
住手
Stop.
住手  住手
Stop it. Stop it.
聽話  住手
Listen, stop.
你常來這里嗎
Come here often?
請問你是
Excuse me?
我是淑女鳥  我們要一起排那部音樂劇
I'm Lady Bird. We're gonna be in the musical together.
我記得你  那天你穿著那條裙子
Oh, yeah. I remember you. You were wearing that dress.
我只是想跟你打聲招呼
Well, I just wanted to say, "What's up,"
排練的時候再見
and I'll see you in rehearsal.
謝謝  我非常激動  你住在這附近嗎
Thanks. I'm super excited. You-- you live in the neighborhood?
沒有  我住在貧民區
No. I'm from the wrong side of the tracks.
-什么  -那是你的家人嗎
- Wh-what? - Is that your family?
是的
Yeah.
人丁興旺啊
There's so many of you.
愛爾蘭天主教家庭
Irish catholic.
很難找個不是我堂表親的姑娘約會
It's hard to find a girl to date that's not my cousin.
好吧  你一定能演好弗蘭克林這個角色的
Well, okay. You're gonna make a great Franklin.
謝謝  不過我想要我  或是他的頭發變卷一點
Oh, thanks. I want my hair-- or his hair-- to be curly, though.
-是啊  -就像
- Yeah. - Like,
就像吉姆·莫里森  典型的七十年代風格
like Jim Morrison. Very '70s.
就像吉姆·莫里森  說得沒錯
Like Jim morrison. Exactly.
-丹尼  -我得走了
- Danny! - I gotta go.
再見
Bye.
誰是吉姆·莫里森來著
Who is Jim Morrison again?
他曾是個搖滾樂隊歌手  傻子  大門樂隊
He was in a rock band, moron. The Doors.
-我就知道  -這是打過雇員折扣的嗎
- I knew that. - This is with your employee discount?
是的  已經打過折了
Yeah. It's already included.
天哪  好吧
Oh, my-- okay.
因為重要的不是正確
Because it's not important to be right.
-重要的只是  -真實
- It's only important to be-- - True.
對了
Exactly!
*昨日已逝  看那美麗的鄉野*
*Yesterday is done see the pretty countryside*
為了充分調動情緒  我們要玩個游戲
To get our emotions going, we're going to play
看誰最先哭出來
first one to cry wins
現在  開始
starting... now.
我也加入
I'm playing too.
帕蒂老師也參加
So is Miss Patty.
對不起
I'm sorry.
不好意思
我聽說他當牧師之前  他結過婚
I heard that before he became a priest, he was married,
有一個兒子叫艾蒂安  十七歲死于吸毒過量
and had a son named Etienne, who died at 17 of a drug overdose,
也有可能是自殺
which maybe was a suicide.
但我媽說如果你對自己的人生那么不上心
But my mom says same difference,
那跟自殺沒什么兩樣
if you're that careless with your life.
我媽來了  我走了
That's her. Gotta go.
-再見  伙計們  -再見
- Bye,guys. - Bye
我差點忘了
I almost forgot.
我給你帶了電動卷發器
I brought you these hot rollers...
用它就能弄吉姆·莫里森的發型了
For your Jim Morrison hair.
-太謝謝你了  -不用謝
- Thank you so much. - You're welcome.
你得教我怎么用
You'll have to show me how to use them.
樂意之至
It would be my pleasure.
它們像一個個精子
They look like sperms.
我剛想起來  我做過一個關于你的夢
I ju-- I just remembered, I had a dream about you.
-是嗎  -是啊
- Really? - Yeah.
-發生什么了  -我們
- What-- what happened? - We were--
我們坐在一個巨大的胡蘿卜上飛向迪士尼樂園
we were flying to Disneyland on a giant carrot.
棒極了
That's awesome.
-我喜歡迪士尼樂園  -我也是
- I love Disneyland. - Me too.
我覺得有點可怕  但是
I think it's kind of scary, but...
我也喜歡
...I also love it.
所以  大家都明白指數的應用規則了嗎
So, everybody clear on applying rules of exponents?
你們在聽我講嗎  別讓我冷場
You guys with me? Don't leave me hanging.
沖我點個頭  好的  說句"我明白了"
Give me a nod. That's good. Maybe even a verbal confirmation.
明白了
Yes.
謝謝你  我就想聽這句
Thank you. That's what I like to hear.
好了  我把批改過的測試卷發下去
All right. So I'm gonna be passing back your graded quizzes.
你們要找出自己為什么做錯了
I urge you to find the problems where you went wrong
修改正確
and work them out.
考得不錯  小朱
Good job, Jules.
從你的卷子上我能看出來
I can tell from your work
你做錯的題其實你會做
you even understood the ones you missed.
媽的
Suck a dick.
我喜歡"小朱"
I like "Jules."
我就是不明白為什么我數學不好
I just don't get why I'm not good at math.
我爸爸數學可好了
My dad is really good in math.
連米格爾都有個數學學位
Even Miguel has a math degree.
或許怪你媽吧
Maybe it's your mom's fault.
-你輸了  朱莉得一分  -不  你看
- You lose! Point Julie! - No. Look.
-祝我好運  -好運
- Wish me luck. - Luck.
想跳舞嗎
Wanna dance?
當然
Hell, yeah.
為圣靈保持六英寸距離
Six inches for the Holy Spirit.
我們的車來了
That's us.
-不  我媽媽來接我  -不  她不會來的
- No. My mom's coming. - No, she's not.
-她會來的  -我們說好在我家過夜的
- Yeah, she is. - The plan was to sleep over at my house.
不  沒關系
No. It's fine.
好吧  再見
Okay. Bye.
再見
Bye.
馬特
Matt.
你出過國嗎
Have you ever been out of the country?
小時候出過
When I was little.
我爸爸以前有一份在巴西的工作
My-- my dad had a job that took him to Brazil.
我看照片想起來的
I remember from the pictures.
我夢想去
My dream to--
-對不起  -不  沒關系  你說
- Sorry. - No. No, you go.
我從沒出過國
I've never been out of the country.
我夢想去巴黎
It's, it's my dream to go to Paris.
巴黎
Paris.
所以我在學法語
That's why I'm taking French.
我媽說法語沒用
My mom said French wasn't useful.
如果你想去巴黎就有用
It is if you wanna go to Paris.
我還是不知道怎么用你給我的卷發棒
I still don't know how to use those rollers that you gave me.
很簡單
It's so easy.
等卷發棒熱起來之后
So, after they heat up--
取一綹頭發
...you-- you take your hair
把頭發這樣卷起來  然后
and you twist the hair like this, and...
拉里  我們還能撐多久
Larry, how long will this hold us?
-我不知道  -總有人得知道
- I don't know. - Well, somebody's gotta know.
我不確定
I'm not sure.
要是有人出點事怎么辦
What happens if somebody gets in an accident?
遣散費馬上就到期了
The severance package expires all at once.
自然年內不可能了
Not within the calendar year.
-她回來了嗎  -要不今晚就算了吧
- Is she home? - Maybe just leave it tonight.
不  她懂事了  她不能再這樣偷溜進來了
No, she knows better. She can't sneak around like this.
瑪麗恩
Marion.
克里斯汀  你不能把房間弄得這么亂
Christine. You can't leave your room like this.
我沒有
I didn't.
沒有一件東西是放好的
None of these things were put away right.
亂糟糟的
They aren't nice.
-克里斯汀  快收拾 -我把衣服收好了
- Christine, now. - I put my clothes away.
-我叫淑女鳥  -不要對我撒謊
- My name is Lady Bird. - Don't lie to me.
這件校服  到周一就會跟一團抹布一樣
This uniform-- this is gonna look like trash on Monday.
這樣放不對  不能把衣服團成一團
This isn't right. We can't treat our clothes like this.
我不知道你的那些有錢的朋友是怎么做的
I don't know what your wealthy friends do--
我怎么放衣服跟你有什么關系
Why do you care what I do to my clothes?
你爸爸沒工作
Your father doesn't have a job.
他失業了
He lost his job.
需要他進來向你解釋這些嗎
Do you need him to come in here and explain that to you?
當然他或許不會這樣做  他是老好人
Of course, he probably wouldn't anyway. He's Mr. Nice guy,
我一直不得不當個壞人
and I always have to be the bad guy.
我們能不能
Can we please just talk...
-你不能邋邋遢遢的  -明天再談
- It can't look like a rag, -...about this tomorrow?
因為那會讓我們一家人看起來像乞丐一樣
Because that makes us look like rags.
想聽真話嗎  這就是真話
You wanna know the truth? Here's the truth.
你那些朋友們的爸爸或許可以雇用你爸
Some of your friends' fathers could employ your father,
但如果這家人看起來不體面  他們就不會雇你爸
and they're not gonna do it if it looks like his family is trash.
你懂嗎
You understand?
要是沒把衣服收好
Didn't you ever go to sleep
你就不睡覺嗎
without putting all your clothes away perfectly?
一次都沒有嗎
Like even once?
你不希望你媽媽沒生氣嗎
And don't you wish your mom hadn't gotten angry?
我媽是個酗酒的虐待狂
My mother was an abusive alcoholic.
所以  你對任何天主教大學都沒興趣
So, I understand you're not interested in any catholic colleges.
沒興趣
No way.
對不起  但是確實沒興趣
Sorry. But yes, no way.
所以你要申請加州大學各分校和州立大學
Then you'll be applying to UCs and state schools.
是的  還有東海岸一些像耶魯一樣的文理學院
Yeah, but also those east coast liberal arts schools like Yale,
不是特指耶魯  因為我可能考不上
but not Yale, because I probably couldn't get in.
你肯定考不上
You definitely couldn't get in.
我的責任之一是幫你認清現實
Part of my job is to help you be realistic.
是啊  好像所有人都有這份責任
Yeah. It seems like everyone's job.
你的SAT成績出奇的好
Your SAT scores are strangely very good.
我給一些你感興趣的
I had placed some calls to
本地大學的校友打了幾通電話
local alumni of the schools you're interested in,
不幸的是  已經沒有面試機會了
but unfortunately, all the interviews are taken.
所以那意味著什么呢
So what does that mean?
意味著你得靠卷面成績進大學了
It means you'll have to get in on how you look on paper.
*夢想不滅  請一直心懷夢想*
*Dreams don't die, so keep an eye on your dream*
*在你發現之前  你已登上山巔*
*And before you know where you are, there you are*
好了  停停停
All right. Stop, stop, stop.
我們是不是該回家了
Should we go home?
我媽總是氣呼呼的
My mom is always mad.
回家晚也沒關系  反正她都是要生氣的
Doesn't matter if I get home late. She'll be mad at me anyway.
-你媽對你真嚴厲  -是的  她很愛我
- Your mom's hard on you. - Yeah, well, she loves me a lot.
選顆我們倆的星星吧
Pick a star for us.
那顆  就在那
That one. Right there.
最亮的旁邊  有顆暗一點的  看到了嗎
Next to the bright one, and then the dim one. You see it?
那就是我們的星星
That's our star.
其實
You know...
你可以摸我的胸  你知道吧
You can touch my boobs, right?
我知道  我很尊重你才沒摸
I know. It's just that I respect you too much for that.
好  太好了
Cool. Awesome.
我非常理解  謝謝你
I totally get that. Thank you.
不用謝
You're welcome.
如果你有胸的話  我也不會摸的
If you had boobs, I wouldn't touch them either.
我很尊重你
I respect you so much...
因為我愛你
Because I love you.
我也愛你
I love you too.
我們的星星就叫克勞德吧
Let's name our star Claude.
你不覺得太做作了嗎
That's pretentious, don't you think?
是法語名  我們給它起什么名字好
It's French. What should we name it?
布魯斯
Bruce.
-我愛你  -我愛你
- I love you! - I love you.
布魯斯
Bruce.
不碰男生的老二是正常的
It's normal to not touch a penis.
我得去上課了
I have to go to class.
-但是我沒課  -我得考過歷史
- But I have free period. - I need to pass history.
我覺得高中學習這方面已經完事了
I think we're done with the learning portion of high school.
-我得走了  -不許走
- I'm gonna go. - No.
我不喜歡一個人待著
I hate being alone.
拜拜  愛你
Bye! Love you!
舊貨商店
丹尼說沒說  他奶奶辦的是不是正式的感恩節晚宴
Did Danny say whether his grandmother has a formal Thanksgiving?
不知道  反正有許多孩子
I don't know. There are a lot of kids,
但是她過著那種40年代的精致生活
but she lives in the fab 40s.
我跟你爸有一次
Oh, well, your dad and I
去那片小區參加過一次晚宴
went to a dinner party once in that neighborhood.
ISC的總裁  還挺正式的
The CEO of ISC. That was pretty formal.
你又不是去參加葬禮
You're not going to a funeral.
我不知道  什么樣算是"富人感恩節"服裝
Well, I don't know. What says "Rich people Thanksgiving"?
我就是覺得
I just think it's such a shame
最后一個感恩節你不跟家人過
that you're spending your last Thanksgiving
反倒去跟一家素未謀面的人過  挺丟人的
with a family you've never met instead of us, but--
不過我知道  你就想那樣
I know. I guess you want it that way.
-你累嗎  -不累
- Are you tired? - No.
-瑪麗恩  -喬伊斯  寶寶怎么樣了
- Hey, Marion. - Hey, Joyce. Hey, how's the baby?
-會爬了  -等會兒去收銀臺我想看看照片
- She's crawling. - No! I wanna see a picture at checkout.
-好啊  -好
- Ok. - Ok.
-你要是累的話  我們坐一會兒  -我不累
- 'Cause if you're tired, we can sit down. - I'm not tired.
因為你剛才拖著腳走路  我看不出你是不是累了
Okay. I just couldn't tell because you were dragging your feet.
我就是看不出來
Well, I just couldn't tell.
你為什么不直接說"抬腳走路"
Why didn't you just say, "Pick up your feet"?
我不知道你是不是累了
I didn't know if you were tired.
-你剛才那叫消極攻擊  -我沒有
- You were being passive-aggressive. - No, I wasn't.
-你太讓人生氣了  -別嚷嚷
- You are so infuriating. - Please stop yelling.
-我沒喊  太完美了  -寶貝  喜歡嗎
- I'm not yelling. Oh! It's perfect! - Honey, do you love it?
因為我的成績冊...
So, because my grade book has...
不見了  那我們這么辦好了
disappeared, here's what we're gonna do.
我需要你們來重新登記成績
I'm gonna count on you to reconstruct it, okay?
我知道你們比誰都清楚自己的成績
Now, I know you all know your grades better than anybody.
我大致知道情況
I have a general idea,
但現在就靠誠信了
but this is all about the honor code right now.
我是A減
A-minus.
我非常確定是A
Pretty sure it was an A.
不是  但...好吧
I'm not, but okay.
是的  相信我  我一眼就能看出來天才
It was. Trust me, I know talent when I see it.
不客氣  不對  謝謝
You're welcome. No. Thank you.
我覺得是B
I think B.
我印象中更像是B減  甚至可能是C加
I thought it was more like b-minus, maybe even c-plus territory?
不  因為我上次測驗考得特別好
No, because I did really well on the last quiz.
我記得你只是稍微好那么一點點
I seem to remember you doing only slightly better.
這樣我的平均分就夠B了
That brought my average up to a B.
行  那就B
Okay. B it is.
這是你的誠信
It's your honor.
淑女鳥  你小情人來了
Lady Bird, your lover awaits!
-你好  丹尼  傳說中的丹尼  -你好
- Hello, Danny! The famous Danny! - Hi.
你可真可愛
Aren't you adorable?
-拉里  你看他可愛吧  -可愛
- Larry, isn't he adorable? - He's adorable.
你要開車接送她  這一晚都拜托你了
You're driving her and everything.
非常感謝你同意淑女鳥
Yeah, well, thank you for letting Lady Bird
參加我祖母的感恩節晚宴  麥克弗森太太
come to my grandmother's Thanksgiving, Mrs. McPherson.
別  不用客氣  叫我瑪麗恩就行
No. No more politeness. Call me Marion.
很高興見到你  麥克弗森先生
Well, nice to meet you, Mr. McPherson.
請叫我拉里·麥克弗森先生
Please, call me Mr. Larry McPherson.
拉里  坐吧  丹尼
Larry. Sit down, Danny.
-喝點什么  -不用麻煩  我不渴
- Can I get you something to drink? - Oh, no, I'm fine.
我是米格爾  她哥
Hey, I'm Miguel, the brother.
我覺得淑女鳥想來個閃亮登場
I think Lady Bird wants to make an entrance.
她好氣我們沒有螺旋式樓梯
She's mad we don't have a spiral staircase.
-謝麗  -什么
- Shelly. - What?
我的名字
Is my name.
有趣的是  我來的路上  經過了火車道
It's funny. On my way over here, I went over the train tracks.
-你走H街過來的  -是的
- Oh, you took h street. - Right. And so,
淑女鳥總說
Lady Bird always says that
自己住在貧民區[鐵軌不好的那一邊]
she lives on the wrong side of the tracks,
我一直以為這是個比喻
but I always thought that was like a metaphor.
沒想到竟然真的有鐵軌
But there are actual train tracks.
太美了
You look amazing!
你拿行李袋干什么
What the hell is in the duffel bag?
不用擔心  天啊
Don't worry about it. Jeez.
-我奶奶會超喜歡這條裙子的  -那就好
- My grandmother will love that dress. - Okay.
等一下
Wait.
-這是你奶奶的房子  -對
- This is your grandma's house? - Yeah.
-天啊  -丹尼  你遲到了
- Oh, my god! - Oh, Danny! You're late.
非常感謝讓我倆來這過節
Well, thank you so much for having us.
-這位是淑女鳥  -你好
- This is Lady Bird. - Hi.
寶貝  我一直都想見見你
Hi, honey. Been anxious to meet you.
所有東薩克拉門托的房子中
Your house is my favorite
-我最喜歡你家這棟  -謝謝
- in all east Sacramento. - Oh, thank you.
美國  里根之國
天啊
Oh, my god!
-這是搞笑吧  -不是
- Is this a joke? - No.
把這里拽出來
Pull these out...
就快做好了  喜歡嗎
Almost done. Do you like it?
真好  我喜歡  能幫我把這桌上的全都疊好嗎
Lovely. I love it. Would you mind doing the whole table for me?
好
Ok.
*將要迸發的夢想*
*Dreams that will explode*
*叫醒沉睡的村莊*
*waking up the countryside*
-怎么知道什么時候起勁  -到時候就知道了
- How do you know when it's working? - You'll know.
-沒有  -沒感覺嗎
- It's not working. - It's not?
-沒有  -我姐說這是上等的好貨
- No. - My sister said this was premium.
-我來勁了  -我也來勁了
- I'm working. - I'm-- I'm working too.
沒有
No.
我胳膊沒知覺了
I can't feel my arms.
那就是來勁了
You're working.
*我不是一個輕易的*
*I'm no easy a*
*安靜的*
*quiet...*
如果丹尼和我結婚了  然后他奶奶死了
If Danny and I get married, and then his grandma died,
我就能繼承那棟夢想中的房子了
I'd inherit the dream house.
不是他父母繼承嗎
Wouldn't his parents get it?
對  我們得把他們殺了
Oh, yeah. We'd have to kill them,
還得把他那幾個哥哥也殺了
and we'd have to kill his older brothers too.
布魯諾老師的太太在哪
Where's Mr. Bruno's wife?
好玩嗎
How's it going?
媽  我們現在真的說不出來話
Mom, we-- we can't really talk right now.
感恩節快樂  我們想你了  淑女鳥
Well, happy Thanksgiving. We missed you, Lady Bird.
-再見  -再見  小鳥
- Bye. - Bye, Birdy.
-再見  謝麗  -再見  謝麗
- Bye, Shelly. - Bye, Shelly.
那根煙為什么看著那么奇怪
Why does that cigarette look so weird?
看著不像是煙
Like, not like a cigarette?
因為這是丁香
'Cause it's a clove.
舔舔嘴唇  所以嘴唇才甜
Lick your lips. That's why they're sweet.
今晚感恩節你不在
Your mom was really sad
你媽特別難過
you weren't here tonight for Thanksgiving.
是的  她討厭我
Yeah, well, she hates me.
你媽媽很善良
She has a big heart, your mom.
我爸媽因為我婚前性行為的事大發雷霆
She took me in after my parents freaked out about...
是她收留了我
whatever, premarital sex.
我很敬佩她
I admire her.
為我們祈禱
Pray for us!
耶穌存心中
Save Jesus in our heart!
到永遠
Forever!
*飛越鄉間田野*
*Flying through the countryside*
*我們一路快樂前行*
*Merrily we roll along, roll along*
*抓住夢想*
*Catching a dream*
別吵了  你們別吵了
Stop fighting! Stop fighting!
*老朋友*
*Hey, old friends*
*我們怎樣才能維持友誼*
*How do we stay old friends*
*它開始時像首歌*
*It started out like a song*
*我和你*
*Me and you*
那倒是  她來了
That's true. There she is.
小朱
Jules.
-你表現太棒了  -謝謝
- You were so good. - Thank you.
真沒想到  這是我妻子貝基
I couldn't believe that. This is my wife Becky.
貝基  這是小朱  我最聰明的學生之一
Becky this is Jules. She's one of my brightest students.
-見到您很高興  -我也是
- It's so-so nice to meet you. - It's nice to meet you too.
-怎么樣  感覺好些了嗎  -有點累
- How we doing? Feeling a little better? - A little tired. Yeah.
那好吧  我得帶她回家了
Okay. All right, I gotta get her home.
有孕在身  不過表演很精彩  小朱
We got the little one, but that was really great, Jules.
謝謝
Thank you.
恭喜
Congratulations.
他根本沒看懂
He didn't understand it.
你們還要尿多久啊
How long do you think you all will pee?
我喝了好多汽水
I drank so much soda.
-去你的  -我來大姨媽了
- Fuck you. - I just got my period.
-該死  -你要去哪兒
- Goddammit. - Where're you going?
男廁所從來都不要排隊
There's never a line in the men's room.
我...
I--
我的天
Oh, my god.
*你闖入我心扉*
*Crash into me, baby*
*我也走到你身邊*
*I come into you*
這襪子質量很不錯的
They're really nice socks.
其實還挺貴的
They're expensive, actually.
它能吸汗
They wick moisture away from your feet.
我的腳就一直出汗
My feet always have moisture.
媽  我很喜歡
Mom, I love them.
抱歉這個圣誕節過得有點寒磣  本想...
I'm sorry it's a small Christmas. We wanted to...
禮物寒磣了點
It's just a little small this year.
很好啊
These are nice.
-你喜歡嗎  -瞧
- Do you like it? - Look.
高爾夫球手從不用減肥
因為他們活在草場上[以蔬菜為食]
-挺好的  -很不錯
- That's good. - That's great.
這怎么能不買  看到就想笑
I had to get it. It makes me laugh.
爸  進來吧
Dad, come in.
你怎么知道是我
How'd you know it was me?
媽媽從不敲門的
Mom doesn't knock.
確實
No, she doesn't.
給你  你的助學金申請表填好了
Here they are. Your completed financial aid applications.
謝謝
Thank you!
-圣誕快樂  -謝謝
- Merry Christmas. - Thank you.
你申請學校還要用錢嗎
Do you need money for the applications?
-我也可以幫你  -不用
- I can help with that too. - No. No.
那個我可以搞定
I've got that.
做暑假工賺的錢夠
Summer job's covered it.
我們規定禁用電腦時間就是不想碰到這種事
This is why we have computer shut off time.
-這是我們的房間  -好的  我知道
- This is our room. - Okay, okay.
你能送我去杰德那里的郵局嗎
Just can you drive me to the post office on Jade?
現在應該還沒關門
It should still be open.
三  二   一
Three, two, one.
新年快樂
Happy new year!
把噴嘴拔出來  然后貼著放進去
So you pull the nozzle out. You tip it in.
《美國人民史》
霍華德·津恩
我很喜歡你的樂隊
I-I like your band.
你和喬納·魯伊茲一起的那個
With Jonah Ruiz,
-"赤落疼年"  -赤裸童年
- lenfance new? - L'enfance nue.
我去看了你們的感恩節演出
Well, I-I saw your Thanksgiving show.
我叫淑女鳥
My name's Lady Bird.
真怪  你居然握手
That's weird. You shake hands.
是啊
Yeah.
我是詹娜的朋友
I'm friends with Jenna and
她總是在說你們的樂隊有多棒
she's always talking about how great your band is.
所以我就想著去現場一探究竟
So I wanted to check it out.
-是啊  詹娜很酷  -沒錯
- Yeah. Jenna's hella tight. - Yeah.
那我們到"杜斯"再見咯
Maybe I'll see you at The Deuce or something, huh?
當然  "杜斯"見
Sure. See you at The Deuce.
我雇你不是讓你調情的
I'm not paying you to flirt.
我沒有
I wasn't flirting.
我倒希望你有呢
I wish you had been.
《創世紀》選讀
A reading from the book of Genesis.
凱爾
"耶和華領著亞布拉罕走到外面說
"The lord took Abram outside and said,
'你向天觀看  數算眾星  能數得過來嗎'
'look up at the sky and count the stars if you can.'
又對他說  '你的后裔將要如此'
just so, he added, 'shall your descendants be.'
亞伯蘭信耶和華
Abram put his faith in the lord.
耶和華就以此為他的義"
Who credited to him as an act of righteousness."
我們第一次做
Okay, the first time we did it,
是去年夏天在他的湖邊小屋里
it was at his lake house last summer.
-太好笑了  -給你
- It was so funny. - Oh, here you go.
馬特叔叔準備的
From uncle Matt.
他和我媽在吵架
I think he and my mom are fighting now,
趁還有得吃就趕緊享受吧
so enjoy the lunches while you can.
不用了謝謝  我在減肥
Oh, no thanks. I'm trying to lose weight.
真的
Really?
做愛倒沒什么
Sex is not a big deal.
只是做到一半的時候我媽給我打電話了
It's just my mom called me during it.
-檢查裙子  -打給了我的手機
- Skirt check. - It was on my cell phone.
她怕出急事給我買的
The one she got me for emergencies.
你接了嗎
Did you pick up?
接了  我說  "媽媽  我現在不方便"
Yeah. I was like, "Um, mom, I can't really talk right now."
是什么急事
What was the emergency?
-什么  -是什么急事
- What? - What was the emergency?
-我姨奶奶死了  -我很遺憾
- Oh, my great aunt died. - I'm so sorry.
她算是自殺的吧
She kinda did it to herself.
我不懂為什么年紀都那么大了還要自殺
Yeah. I don't know why you'd do that if you're already so old.
各位
Ladies.
裙子
Skirts.
我得把這件事寫在評語里了  沃爾頓小姐
I'm going to write you a citation, Miss Walton.
不要再穿短裙了
No more short skirts.
莎拉·瓊就是對我有意見
Sarah Joan is all up in my junk.
她就是個婊子
She's a cunt.
小鳥  你明明喜歡她
Birdy, you like her.
對  但她是個婊子
Yeah, but she's a cunt.
我知道怎么報復莎拉·瓊了
I have an idea of how to get Sarah Joan back.
-怎么做  -下午你就知道了
- How? - You'll see this afternoon.
不行  今天下午我們要面試角色
No, we have auditions this afternoon.
對了  我其實不太想參演那部話劇
Oh, right. I mean, uh, I don't think I want to do the play.
三點教師停車場見
Meet me at the teacher's parking lot at 3.
-我會把東西都準備好  -好的
- I'll have the materials. - Okay.
等下  你叫什么來著
Wait, what was your name?
淑女鳥
Lady Bird.
-真怪  -各位
- Weird. - Ladies.
我們得做個決定
We have a decision to make.
舞會主題  目前呼聲最高的有
Prom themes. Top options so far,
畢業舞會主題
全球各大城市
Cities of The World,
永恒之火  還有電影
Eternal Flame, and Movies.
拉維亞奇神父哪兒去了
Where is Father Leviatch?
好了  大家都單膝跪地
All right, let's have everyone take a knee.
-什么  -隨便坐
- What? - Cozy sit.
我知道你們都很想念拉維亞奇神父
Now, I know you all miss Father Leviatch,
我們這些哥們兒也很想
and I can tell you that the brothers do too.
但我會盡全力做好這件事
But I'm gonna give this thing my best shot.
雖然我是校橄欖球二隊的教練
Now, usually I'm the JV football coach,
但依我看  演話劇和比賽是一回事
but from what I can see, a play is a play.
淑女鳥呢
Where's Lady Bird?
和她剛認的好閨蜜在一起
She's with her new best friend.
她覺得自己太酷了  演話劇配不上她
She thinks she's too cool for theater.
請你們都把劇本拿出來
If you can pull out your-your scripts,
我給你們每個角色都編好了號
I've assigned a number to each of your roles.
我現在把舞臺調度畫到黑板上
And, uh, I'm gonna put the blocking up here on the board,
你們可以抄到
and then if you guys can transcribe
自己的劇本上  這樣就行
that back in your play books, that'd be great.
角色怎么分的啊
Who's playing what part?
我讓帕蒂老師都分好了  畢竟她跟你們熟
I had Miss Patty here assign roles, since she knows you all.
《暴風雨》
那帕蒂老師  把角色分配都報一遍吧
So, uh, call them out, Miss Patty.
好的  丹尼飾演普洛斯彼羅
Okay, Prospero. Danny.
丹尼  很好  你是一號角色
Danny. Nice. That's Role One.
剛嫁給耶穌
等等  你住在哪里
Wait. Where do you live?
四十多街
Oh, um, the 40s.
我們家剛開始就住那里
That's where our starter house was.
哪條街
Which street?
44街
Um, 44th.
那座藍色的三層房子
It's the three-story blue one
白色的百葉窗  屋前還有面美國國旗
with the white shutters and the American flag in the front.
我知道那座房子
Yeah. I know that one.
你想現在就過去吃飯嗎
Do you want to go over there right now and eat?
我住在格蘭尼特灣  不然我就提議去那里了
I live in Granite Bay, otherwise I'd say let's go there.
其實  我覺得我們可以去"杜斯"
Actually, I was thinking maybe we should go to the Deuce.
我還跟凱爾說過來著  他說
I was talking to Kyle about it, and he was like,
"雖然那兒挺爛的  但我們在那兒見吧"
"Whatever it's lame, but maybe I'll see you there."
你怎么認識凱爾的
How do you know Kyle?
我媽媽讓我在新海爾維希找了份工作
Oh, my mom made me get a job at New Helvetia
去學學"責任感"
to learn, like, "Responsibility."
反正我們一起在那里玩
Anyway, we hang out there.
沒錯  凱爾很棒
Yeah. Kyle's awesome.
那我們就"杜斯"起來吧
Let's Deuce it up.
好的  看清楚了  一號角色
Okay, guys. Now, look. Role One, right?
你跑起來  到右前方來
You're gonna run, kind of, a skinny post right up front.
我要你直視觀眾  好嗎
I want you to look straight at the audience, okay.
如果有人經過你
Don't be looking around
不要左顧右盼或者跟誰說話
and blabbing at anybody if they walk by ya.
八號九號十號  你們迅速過來  到這個位置
Eight, Nine, Ten. You're coming in hard, right here.
因為觀眾們會喜歡的
'Cause these guys are gonna love it.
不要自言自語
Don't talk amongst yourselves.
慢慢地上場  唱著歌
Now, coming in slow, we're singing.
這是在唱歌  粗線表示唱歌
This is singing. Wide lines are singing.
唱著歌  唱著歌
We're singing. We're singing.
丹尼還沒開始唱  就他一個人
Danny's not singing yet. He's all alone.
繼續唱  八號九號十號  你們沖上臺
Singing. Eight, nine, ten... You come in hot!
沖上臺
You come in hot!
-這里就是"杜斯"  -沒錯
- This is the Deuce? - Yeah.
-是個停車場  -是的
- It's a parking lot? - Yeah.
我們剛從一個停車場到了另一個停車場
We were in one parking lot and we went to another parking lot?
凱爾  淑女鳥跟我剛剛裝飾了一下修女的車
Hey, Kyle. Lady Bird and I just decorated the nun-mobile.
搞成了"剛嫁給耶穌"
Like, just married to Jesus.
那很酷啊
That's hella tight.
你們可真大膽
What you do is very baller.
-你們非常地無政府主義  -沒錯
- You're very anarchist. - Yeah.
去他們的
Fuck 'em.
別擔心  我不會告發你們的
Don't worry, I'm not gonna snitch on you.
我希望你不會  不然我會殺你全家的
Well, I hope not 'cause I'd fuckin' kill your family.
-什么  -對不起
- What? - Sorry.
那...那只是夸張的說法
T-- that-that was an exaggeration.
沒關系
It's okay.
我爸爸得了癌癥  所以
My dad has cancer, so
我想是上帝在替我們殺人
I guess god's doing that for us.
我很抱歉
Oh, I'm sorry.
你在新海爾維希打工  是嗎
You work at New Helvetia, right?
是的
Right.
我能要你的電話號嗎
Can I get your number?
我們想在那邊演出
We were looking to set up more gigs down there.
當然沒問題
Definitely.
這是我父母的電話
It's my parents number.
你沒有手機嗎
You don't have a cell phone?
-沒有  -乖孩子
- Nah. - Good girl.
用不著政府在我們身上放追蹤器
Government didn't have to put tracking devices on us.
我們主動就裝上了  還花自己的錢
We bought them and put them on ourselves.
我沒有追蹤器
I don't own a tracking device.
不不不  我說的是手機
No, no, no. The cell phones.
你明白了嗎
You see?
是啊  我知道
Yeah. I know.
你總會有的  每個人都會有一部
I mean, you'll have one eventually. Everyone's gonna have one.
然后  就只是時間問題了
And then, it'll be a matter of time.
什么的時間問題
Before what?
把手機裝進我們的大腦
Before they put them in our brains.
你想要我怎樣
What do you want from me?
說啊
Yes?
我...我奶奶要我跟你說
My-my grandma wanted me to tell you that
她圣誕節的時候很想念你
she missed you at Christmas.
是啊  反正我也去不了
Yeah. Well, I couldn't have gone anyway.
我媽媽對感恩節的事很不高興
My mom was pissed about Thanksgiving.
你媽媽瘋了  我很怕她
Your mom is crazy. I'm scared of her.
她沒瘋  她只是很善良
She's not crazy. She's just, you know, she has a big heart.
她很溫暖
She's very warm.
我不覺得你媽媽很溫暖
I don't find your mother warm.
-你不覺得  -不  不  她是很暖
- You don't? - No. No, she's warm. Yeah.
但她也有點嚇人
But she's also, kind of scary.
人不可能既溫暖又嚇人
Well, you can't be scary and warm.
-我覺得有可能  你媽媽就是  -你是個同性戀
- I think you can. Your mom is. - You're gay.
媽的
Fuck me.
不要告訴別人好嗎  求你
Can you not tell anyone, please?
我為一切道歉
I'm so sorry about everything.
我非常羞恥
I'm so ashamed of all of it.
只是...情況很不樂觀
It's just... it's going to be bad
我只是需要點時間
and I just need a little bit of time
來想想怎么告訴我的父母...
to figure out how I'm going to tell my mom and dad and--
別擔心
Don't worry.
我不會說出去的
I won't tell.
沒事了
It's okay.
你有什么撐下去的方式嗎
And do you have a support system?
你是指什么
What do you mean?
你出現這種感覺時會找誰傾訴
Who do you turn to when you feel this way?
沒有誰吧
No one, I guess.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
不  別這樣
No, don't be sorry.
沒有對錯之分
There's no wrong answer.
別告訴你的女兒
Please don't tell your daughter.
不會  當然不會
No. Of course not.
當然不會
Of course not.
記住  你本是塵土  仍要歸于塵土
Remember that you are dust and to dust you will return.
這是一個新系統
It's a new system.
只需要輸入你的社保號  然后...
You just enter your social security number and...
-戴維斯分校  -戴維斯分校很好
- Davis? - Davis is good.
-也許你應該看看  -那里只有半小時車程
- Maybe you shoulda looked at it. - It's only half an hour away.
-開得快都用不了半小時  -我在那里上的研究生
- Less if you're driving fast. - I went to graduate school there.
很多聰明的人都上的戴維斯分校
Lots of smart people go to Davis.
我還以為伯克利分校一定會錄取我
I thought Berkeley had to accept me.
你跟米格爾就上的那里  我是校友親屬
You and Miguel went there. I'm a legacy.
如果我們不捐錢的話就不算
Uh, not if we don't give money.
-而且你成績很爛  -你又懂些什么
- And you get bad grades. - And what do you know about it?
-你什么意思  -沒什么
- Meaning? - Nothing.
-不  你在暗示什么  -沒什么
- No. What are you implying? - Nothing!
你個該死的種族歧視者
You fucking racist!
-我什么都沒說  -我申請的時候都沒提種族
- I didn't say anything! - I didn't put down my race!
是嗎  我保證他們不知道  米格爾
Oh, yeah. I'm sure they had no idea, Miguel!
你他媽的就是個惡魔
You're actually fucking evil.
-你有什么毛病  -去  回你房間去
- What is wrong with you? - Go. Go to your room.
-我可不是五歲孩子  -我可沒把你教成這樣
- I'm not five! - I didn't raise you like this.
我哪里都不用去
I don't have to go anywhere.
我他媽的才不會上個
I'm not going to a fucking university
以農學院聞名的破大學
that's famous for its fucking agricultural school!
還有米格爾和謝麗
And Miguel and Shelly,
你倆臉上掛著那些破玩意兒永遠找不到工作
you'll never get jobs with all that shit in your face.
冰箱里的東西隨便拿吧
Um, help yourself to anything in the fridge.
我爸媽在樓上  但如果你要喝酒他們也不會在意
My parents are upstairs, but they don't care if you drink.
很好
Okay. Cool.
我討厭那個
I hate that shit.
但是你抽煙
But you smoke.
我只抽手卷煙
I smoke hand-rolled cigarettes.
從來不抽工業化生產的
Never industrially produced.
也從不抽丁香煙
Never cloves.
丁香煙怎么了
What's wrong with cloves?
又吸不到丁香  有什么意義
Can't inhale cloves. What's the point?
就是不該吸那個
You're not supposed to.
我小時候最開始就抽丁香煙
Well, cloves were what I first smoked when I was young.
所以  是一種習慣
So, you know, it's a force of habit.
里面有玻璃纖維
It has fiberglass.
-真的嗎  -是的
- Really? - Yeah.
自己卷的最好了
Rolling your own is best.
還有
Also, like...
我想盡可能避免參與經濟活動
I'm trying as much as possible not participate in our economy.
我不喜歡錢
I don't like money.
所以...
So...
我盡量只物物交換
I'm trying to live by bartering alone.
但上天主教學校要收錢吧
But doesn't catholic school cost money?
對  我家里特別喜歡這個教區
Yeah. The diocese we're in are super into it.
我爸當時很希望我
It mattered to my dad that...
上澤維爾高中
I go to Xavier, so...
我就是想讓他開心
Just trying to make him happy.
我還沒準備好
I don't wanna have sex yet.
-我還是第一次  -我也是
- I haven't had sex yet. - Me neither.
-沒和別人做過  -我也是
- With another person. - Nope. Me either.
-真的嗎  -嗯
- Really? - Yeah.
我的天
Oh, my god!
是美黑床
It's the tanning bed.
朱莉在的話  一定樂壞了
Julie will love this.
朱莉是誰
Who's Julie?
澤維爾高中
淑女鳥  我們只有一個衛生間  別鎖門
Lady Bird. You can't lock the door when we have one bathroom.
抱歉
Sorry, sorry, sorry.
只有這里  我才能有點私人空間
It's just this is the only place I can get any privacy.
你必須得用兩條毛巾嗎
You really need to use two towels?
不用
Uh, no.
-不用  -如果你要用兩條
- I guess no. - If you need to use two towels,
記得跟我說  不然我一整天都受影響
you just have to say because this affects my whole day.
因為我上班前得洗衣服
Because I have to do laundry before work
如果需要我洗兩條毛巾  提前打招呼
and I need to know if there's more towels that I need to wash.
我只用一條  抱歉
I just need one. Sorry.
好  我照下鏡子  我得走了
Okay. Well, let me get to the mirror, I've gotta get going.
你覺得什么時候第一次做愛比較合適
When do you think is a normal time to have sex?
-你做愛了  -沒
- You're having sex? - No.
大學比較好
Um, college is good.
大學  而且像我們談過的  做好保護措施
I think college and use protection like we talked about.
好吧
Okay.
爸爸得抑郁癥了嗎
Is dad depressed?
怎么了
Why do you ask that?
我看到藥了  上面寫著爸爸的名字
The pills. They have dad's name on them.
你爸已經得抑郁癥很多年了
Dad's been struggling with depression for years.
我不知道
I didn't know that.
金錢并不是成功與否的體現
Money is not life's report card.
他是因為錢抑郁的嗎
He's depressed about money?
成功也不能說明什么
Being successful doesn't mean anything in and of itself.
只是說明你成功了而已
It just means that you're successful.
但是成功就是成功了
Yeah, but then you're successful.
但并不意味著你過得幸福
But that doesn't mean that you're happy.
可他也不幸福
But he's not happy.
我得離開薩克拉門托
I have to get out of Sacramento.
為什么
Why?
待在這里就是精神折磨
Because it's soul killing.
這里是加州的中西部
It's the midwest of California.
有句話不是說
Isn't there a thing, like,
"放眼全球  立足本地"
"Think globally, act locally"?
說這話的人  一定不住在薩克拉門托
I feel that the person who said that didn't live in Sacramento.
我喜歡這里
I love it here.
我想把女兒送去圣心高中念書
I want to send my daughters to Immaculate Heart.
我想做媽媽
I wanna-- you know, I wanna be a mom.
至少舊金山也行
At least go to San Francisco.
我不喜歡山
I don't like hills.
從簡單的開始  x加3乘x加2
Start simple with x plus three times x plus two.
-乘法分配律怎么用  -朱莉
- Now if we use foil, where do we start? - Julie?
朱莉
Julie?
Julie.
你叫朱莉干什么
What do you want from Julie?
達琳  能讓我們單獨聊聊嗎
Darlene, can you excuse us?
達琳也聽著
Darlene's staying.
為什么你沒上代數二的課
Why aren't you in Algebra 2?
-我換課了  -為什么
- I switched sections. - Why?
有了詹娜和凱爾還不夠嗎
Aren't Jenna and Kyle enough?
很抱歉讓你嫉妒了
I'm sorry that you're jealous.
詹娜那么蠢
Jenna's a moron, you know.
她不蠢  她還修微積分呢
She's not. She's in AP Calculus.
我不是說她智商蠢
She's a moron in a deeper sense.
你根本不了解她
You don't even know her.
帕蒂老師給你分配了角色
Miss Patty assigned you a role by the way,
你都沒出現
you just never showed up to claim it!
-什么角色  -《暴風雨》
- What role? - The Tempest!
-根本就沒有暴風雨這個角色  -這可是標題角色
- There is no role of The Tempest! - It is the titular role!
只不過是硬編出來的  好讓所有人都參與
No, it's a made up thing so we all can participate!
只要你不是主角
You can't do anything
就什么都不做了嗎
unless you're the center of attention, can you?
對啊  你知道你媽的胸是假的嗎
Yeah. Well, you know your mom's tits, they're fake. Totally fake!
她不過是19歲時做錯了決定
She made one bad decision at 19!
是兩個決定
Two bad decisions!
15歲  這個女孩就懷孕了
And at 15, this girl was pregnant.
她決定去打胎
She decided that she was going to get an abortion.
有道理  確實應該這樣做
It made sense. It was the right thing to do.
-她靜坐著  -我猜她沒打
- She was sitting there... - Let me guess, she didn't get it.
腦海里突然冒出一個聲音
...and something deep inside of her said,
-不要  -我說吧
- no! - bingo.
猜猜這個女孩是誰
Anyone want to guess who this woman is?
這邊的女生
The young lady right here.
-你嗎  -不  不是我
- You? - No. It was not me.
你朋友嗎
Um, your friend?
不是
No.
故事中的這個女孩
The girl in the story was...
是我母親
my mother.
我就是她決意留下的那個孩子
I am that baby that she decided not to abort.
那可能就是我
That could have been me.
那可能就是我的命運
That could have been my fate.
有些東西雖然看起來丑
Just because something looks ugly
但并不一定道義上就是錯的
doesn't mean it's morally wrong.
你說什么  女士
What did you say, ma'am?
-沒什么  -請講
- Nothing. - Please. Share.
我說
I said,
"有些東西雖然看起來丑
"Just because something looks ugly
但并不一定道義上就是錯的"
doesn't mean that it's morally wrong."
你覺得胎兒死掉在道義上是對的
You think dead children aren't morally wrong?
不  我只是說
No. I'm just saying that
要是你在我大姨媽來的時候
if you took up close pictures of my vagina
拍一張我私處的特寫  也會很惡心
while I was on my period, it would be disturbing,
但并不說明來姨媽就是錯
but it doesn't make it wrong.
你說什么
Excuse me?
如果你媽真的打了胎
Listen. If your mother had had the abortion,
我們也不用坐這這么久  聽這個破會
we wouldn't have to sit through this stupid assembly.
停學  怎么回事
Suspended? How does this happen?
我們做的一切都是為了你  一切
Everything we do is for you. Everything.
你以為我想開那輛破車四處晃嗎
Do you think I like driving that car around?
-不  -我想嗎
- No. - Do you?
-不  -你以為我愿意在精神病院
- No. - Do you think I like working double shifts
兩班倒嗎
at the psych hospital?
-不  -你必須得去天主教學校
- No. - You needed to go to the catholic school
因為在公立學校
because your brother saw somebody knifed
你哥哥親眼看見別人被捅了
in front of him at the public school.
你想這樣嗎  拉里  你在電腦前忙什么
Is that what you want? Larry, what are you doing on the computer?
-沒什么  -你以為我和你爸不知道
- Nothing. - You think your dad and I don't know
你覺得我們給你丟臉嗎  你爸知道
how ashamed that you are of us? Your dad knows.
你爸知道  為什么每天送你上學
Your dad knows why you ask him to drop you off
離學校還有一街區  你就提前下車
a block away from school every day.
-爸  我不是那個意思  -你知道他多難過嗎
- Dad, I didn't mean to. - You made him feel horrible!
-你知道嗎  -對不起
- Horrible! You know that? - I'm sorry.
瑪麗恩  你沒必要提這個
Marion, you didn't have to bring that up.
不  拉里  你別裝老好人了
No, Larry, you can't just be the nice guy.
得讓她知道
She has to know.
她得明白你的感受
She has to know how you feel.
要不然她還以為自己能口無遮攔
Otherwise, she's just gonna think she can say anything at all,
傷人而不自知
and nobody ever gets hurt.
貧民區
Wrong side of the tracks!
-我不是那個意思  -呵呵
- I didn't mean it that way. - Yeah.
-我在開玩笑  -是  這是玩笑
- It was a joke. - Yeah. It's just a joke mom and dad.
爸媽才不會在意
They don't care.
我們也沒想到25年了還要住在這里
We didn't think we'd be in this house for 25 years.
我們以為會搬去更好的地方
We thought we would've moved some place better.
不管我們給了你什么  永遠都不夠
Whatever we give you, it's never enough.
-永遠都不夠  -夠了
- It's never enough. - It is enough.
你知道養你這么大花了多少錢嗎
Do you have any idea what it costs to raise you?
你又知道你每天浪費了多少錢嗎
And how much you're just throwing away every day?
給我個數
Give me a number.
什么
What?
給我個數
Give me a number.
我不明白
I don't understand.
告訴我  養大我  你花了多少錢
You give me a number for how much it cost to raise me.
我長大了要賺很多錢
And I'm going to get older and make a lot of money,
開張支票  把我欠你的都還你
and write you a check for what I owe you.
這樣我就不用跟你浪費口舌了
So that I never have to speak to you again.
我可不相信
Well I highly doubt that
能找到那么好的工作
you will be able to get a job good enough to do that.
昨晚對巴格達的襲擊
So the attack on Baghdad last night,
絕對令人震驚
it was absolutely unbelievable.
沒錯  昨晚襲擊的規模  許多美國士兵...
That's right. Yeah, the likes of which, uh, many US...
-喂  -是我  詹娜
- Hello? - Hey, it's me, Jenna.
你在學校給我打電話嗎
Are you calling me from school?
沒有  我們提早放學了
No. We got out early
所有愛爾蘭女生沒到中午就喝成爛泥了
'cause all the Irish girls got totally sloshed by noon.
對  圣帕特里克節快樂
Oh, right. Happy St. Patrick's day.
同樂  我猜她們一直在
Yeah. I guess they'd been stockpiling
往棉條機里偷偷塞小瓶酒
mini liquor bottles in the tampon machine,
現在都吐得七葷八素的
and now they're all throwing up.
其他人都提早離校了
Everyone else got out early.
好了  猜猜我在哪
So, guess where I am.
我不知道  在哪
I don't know. Where?
叮咚  我在門口
Ding dong. I'm outside.
-什么  -我就在門口
- What? - I'm standing outside.
不  快走
No. Just leave.
快走
Leave.
-該死  -你好
- Fuck! - Hello.
這才是你家
So this is your house?
對
Yeah.
那棟房子里的女士徹底蒙了
That lady in the other house was totally freaked out.
她是我朋友的奶奶  那是她家
That's my friend's grandma. That's her house.
那你為什么說是你家
Why did you say it was your house?
我希望自己能住在那里
I wished I lived in that house.
我一點都想不明白
I don't even sort of understand
怎么會有人撒這種謊
why somebody would lie about that.
我沒撒謊
I-I didn't lie.
你就有  你這個騙子
You lied. You're a liar.
我討厭不誠實的人
I hate dishonesty.
對不起
I'm sorry.
那我就接受道歉吧
Apology accepted, I guess.
我們還是朋友嗎
Are we still friends?
如果你還是凱爾的女朋友
I mean, if you're still Kyle's girlfriend,
我們還會再見面的
then yeah, I guess I'll see you around.
機群離地面近的時候
Mortar rounds fired at the camp that will fly over them
迫擊炮朝會朝飛過的機群射擊
if they are down below on surface of the ground.
這樣難度很大  相信我
And that is hard work, indeed. Believe me.
我們必須...
We've had to do it...
我準備好了
I'm ready.
什么
What?
我準備好做愛了
I'm ready to have sex.
好
Okay.
太好了
Great.
你好熟練
You're so dexterous with that.
謝謝
Thanks.
-還好嗎  -還好
- You okay? - Yeah.
你是不是...
Are you...
-是不是射了  -對  對
- Are you done? - Yeah. Yes.
抱歉  我不太懂
Sorry. I was confused.
-你,,,  -怎么了
- You have like... - What?
-你好像流血了  -什么
- You have some sort of like blood. - What?
我去
Shit!
我偶爾會流鼻血
I get nosebleeds.
-給  -謝謝
- Here. - Thanks.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
不用  我沒事
No. I'm good.
還記得以前很流行扎染嗎
Remember when tie-dye was an activity?
那件不是我做的
Oh, I didn't make that shirt.
我爸媽在海濱牧場給我買的
My parents got it for me at sea ranch.
仔細看能看出上面寫著海濱牧場
You can read sea ranch if you look close.
鏡頭切到十年后
Cut to ten years later.
什么
What?
就像十年前你才上一年級
Like how ten years ago, you were in first grade.
現在切到...
Now we cut to...
你的"切到"是什么意思
What does cut to mean to you?
或者  他還不諳世事
Or like, you know, little did he know.
完全聽不懂你在說什么
Nothing you're saying is making any sense.
現在我們都不是處了
How we're not virgins now.
我們破了苞
We deflowered each other.
我們把第一次給了彼此
We have each other's flowers.
抱歉
Sorry.
我太開心了
I'm just happy.
我的初夜不是給了你
I didn't lose my virginity to you.
等等
Wait...
什么
What?
我的第一次給了凱西·杜瓦爾
I lost my virginity to Cassy Duvall.
你說什么
Excuse me?
你說你是處
You said you were a virgin.
我沒有  因為我不是
No, I didn't. 'Cause I'm not.
-我已經兩年沒撒謊了  -老天
- And I haven't lied in two years. - Oh, Jesus.
真的  我睡了大概有六個人了
Yeah. I probably slept with, like, six people.
你連是不是六個都不確定嗎
You don't even know if it's six people?
我又沒刻意去記
I don't keep a list.
為什么不記
Why wouldn't you keep a list?
我們才上高中
We're in high school.
你為什么...
Why are you-- what?
你這么激動做什么
Why are you getting so moody?
你就是說過你是處
You did say you were a virgin.
是你自己亂猜的吧
I think you might've made an assumption.
剛剛那一切都不該發生
I just had a whole experience that was wrong.
你看  你又要生氣了
Look, you're deciding to be upset.
不  我已經生氣了
No. I am upset.
因為你想要生氣  別為這個對我發火
Because you're deciding to be. Don't be mad at me for this.
這樣太傻了  你不能為了
It's stupid. You can't be mad at me
我控制不了的事情生我的氣
for something I have no control over.
我只希望第一次是很特別的
I just wanted it to be special.
為什么
Why?
你一生中會有那么多不特別的性愛
You're gonna have so much unspecial sex in your life.
我在上面  誰他媽第一次在上面
I was on top! Who the fuck is on top their first time?
你知道自從我們入侵伊拉克以來
You have any, like, awareness of how many civilians we've killed
-死了多少平民嗎  -閉嘴
- since the invasion in Iraq started-- - Shut up!
閉嘴
Shut up.
讓人傷心的事有很多  不止是戰爭
Different things can be sad. It's not all war.
我們還要一起去舞會嗎
Are we still going to prom together?
好
Sure.
我還以為米格爾來接我
I thought Miguel was gonna pick me up.
我下班就過來了  這樣更方便
Well, I was just arriving from work and it was easier.
你還好嗎
You okay?
親愛的
Honey.
他...
He...
沒事了
It's okay.
這件毛衣是誰的
What's this sweater?
這件是  我朋友詹娜給我的
This is... my friend, Jenna, gave it to me.
詹娜是誰
Who's Jenna?
我朋友
My friend.
想來一次我們最愛的周日活動嗎
You wanna do our favorite Sunday activity?
我只輪一班
I don't have a second shift.
好
Yeah.
攻擊一波波襲來
The attack came in waves,
巡航導彈轟炸之后是F117隱形轟炸機
cruise missiles, followed by the F117 stealth bombers
所謂的"地堡終結者"炸彈
with so-called bunker buster bombs.
一枚瞄準目標的...
With target a bunker believed...
淑女鳥  有幾封給你的信
Lady Bird, a bunch of things arrived for you.
不是吧
Holy shit!
-什么時候有人給你寄信了  -就是有
- Since when do you get mail? - I get mail.
不論你想干什么  都不會有好下場的
Whatever you're up to, it's not gonna end well.
哥倫比亞大學  紐約
回復  本科入學申請
很遺憾地通知您
無法通過您的申請
候補名單
太棒了
Yes!
現在的程序員就是小屁孩
These programmers nowadays are like kids, man.
是啊
I know.
所以你一定能在我身上發現不同之處
But that's why I think with me, you'll find something different.
是  他們真的乳臭未干
Yeah, but they're like babies.
確實  太瘋狂了
I hear you. It's wild.
所以我重新回到學校
Which is why I went back to school
邊在ISC工作邊拿下了
and got my MBA at UC Davis
加州大學戴維斯分校的工商管理碩士
while still working at ISC.
-肯定很辛苦吧  -確實
- That must've been a lot of work. - It was.
但我聽說ISC要倒閉了
I heard ISC's closing now though.
聽說是
I heard. Yes.
炒你魷魚的傻子要關門大吉了
So the assholes who fired you are now closing up shop.
-感覺很爽  -是啊
- Feels good. - Yeah.
還有什么事嗎
What else is supposed to happen?
我想我們可以
Oh, I, uh, thought we'd...
聊聊這個職位
talk about the position.
怎么樣
How'd it go?
我們去買一大包多力多滋去車里吃
Let's go buy a big bag of doritos and eat them in the car
-慶祝你進候補名單  -好
- to celebrate your wait list. - Okay.
吃多力多滋和進候補名單的事別告訴媽媽
But don't tell mom about the doritos or the wait list.
你好  兒子
Hi, son.
等下  你在這做什么
Wait. What are you doing here?
我想  我們應聘的是同一職位
I guess we're, uh, going for the same job then.
看來是的
Looks like it.
-加油  -謝謝
- Go get 'em. - Thanks.
-這邊走嗎  -是的
- This-this way? Okay. - Yeah, yeah.
我知道"剛嫁給耶穌"那件事是你干的
I know it was you who did the just married thing.
不是我干的
It wasn't me.
我不會懲罰你的
I'm not going to punish you.
為什么
Why not?
很有趣
It was funny.
吉娜修女和我一路開回家
Sister Gina and I drove all the way home
都沒有發現人們在沖我們按喇叭
before we noticed people were honking.
真的嗎
Really?
其實  我并不是"剛剛"嫁給耶穌的
To be fair, I wasn't just married to Jesus.
我嫁了有40年了
It's been 40 years.
那他可真走運
Well, he's a lucky guy.
我讀了你的申請文書
I read your college essay.
很明顯你熱愛薩克拉門托
You clearly love Sacramento.
-我有嗎  -你寫薩克拉門托的筆觸
- I do? - You write about Sacramento
細膩又親切
so affectionately and with such care.
我只是描繪這里而已
Well, I was just describing it.
但里面充滿了愛
Well, it comes across as love.
好吧  我想我是留心了
Sure. I guess I pay attention.
你不覺得它們是一回事嗎
Don't you think they are maybe the same thing?
愛和留心
Love and attention?
我想你在大學里不會再跳舞了
Guess you won't be going to any dances in college.
這是我們最后一次跳了
This is our last one.
如果你還對戲劇感興趣的話
You know Davis has a terrific theater
戴維斯分校有個很好的劇院
if you're still interested in theater.
-你感興趣嗎  -我可能對演戲不太在行
- Are ya? - I'm probably no good at acting.
為什么我就不能像雜志上那些女生一樣
Why don't I look like the girls in the magazines?
舞會前我見不到這位凱爾真是太遺憾了
It's too bad I can't meet this Kyle before prom.
他不再是我的男朋友了
Well, he's not my boyfriend anymore.
他可能之前也不算
I mean, maybe he never even was.
我還是想見見他
Well, I'd still like to meet him.
該死  衣服太緊了
It's too tight. Fuck.
我和你說了別吃第二份通心粉了
Well, I suggested you not have that second helping of pasta.
-媽媽  -親愛的  你好像有些沮喪
- Mom. - Honey, you seem upset about it
-我只是想幫忙  -你要讓我患上厭食癥了
- and I'm trying to help. - You're giving me an eating disorder.
我真希望我有厭食癥
I wish I could get an eating disorder.
我很喜歡
I love it.
會不會太粉嫩了
Is it too pink?
怎么了
What?
你為什么不能說我看起來很漂亮
Why can't you say I look nice?
我以為你根本不會在意我的想法
I thought you didn't even care what I think.
-我還是希望你覺得我很美  -好的  對不起
- I still want you to think I look good. - Okay. I'm sorry.
我只是實話實說  你想讓我撒謊嗎
I was telling you the truth. You want me to lie?
不  我是只想
No. I mean, I just wish...
我只是
I just...
我希望你喜歡我
I wish that you liked me.
我當然愛你
Of course I love you.
但你喜歡我嗎
But do you like me?
我希望你能成為
I want you to be
你能成為的最好的那一個自己
the very best version of yourself that you can be.
如果現在就是最好的呢
What if this is the best version?
你看起來很漂亮
You look really pretty.
-真的嗎  -是的
- Really? - Yeah.
你看起來像樂隊里的酷女孩
You look like a badass girl in a band.
謝謝
Thanks.
我舞伴來了
I guess that's my date.
你不會跟一個按喇叭的人上車吧
You aren't gonna get in a car with a guy who honks, are ya?
我想我會的
I think, yes, I am.
我來給你照張相
Let me get your picture.
你媽特生氣  她今天得輪兩次班
Your mom's pissed, she had to work a double.
就算是你也該值得更好的
Even you deserve better than this.
玩得開心
Have a good time.
祝你好運
Yeah. Good luck.
-再見  -再見
- See ya. - See ya.
-我覺得她很怪  -她是很怪
- I think she's weird. - She is weird.
伙計們
Hey, guys.
那我就坐副駕好了
I guess I'll just sit shotgun.
好的
Yeah.
-你今天很帥  凱爾  -你也好美
- You look really nice, Kyle. - You look good.
謝謝
Thanks.
你好嗎  伙計
Hey, what's going on, man?
嗯  聽起來不錯
Yeah. Okay, that sounds great.
好的
Okay.
你們想翹了舞會  直接去邁克家嗎
Hey, do you guys wanna ditch prom and just go to Mike's instead?
好啊  我討厭跳舞
Yeah. I hate dances.
好的
Yes.
好的  不去舞會
Yeah. Okay. No prom.
我真是煩這首歌
I fucking hate this song.
我很喜歡
I love it.
實際上我想去參加舞會
I actually want to go to prom.
好吧
Okay. Yeah. I mean...
我不太想去
I don't really want to do that.
你能把我送到我朋友朱莉家嗎
Can you-- can you take me to my friend, Julie's house, please?
當然
Sure.
誰是朱莉
Who's Julie?
她是我閨蜜
She's my best friend.
朱莉  親愛的
Julie, honey?
有人來看你了
There's someone here to see you.
-你還好嗎  -嗯  還行
- Are you okay? - Fine. I'm fine.
出什么事了
What happened?
沒什么  真的
Nothing really. Nothing.
你為什么哭呢
Why are you crying?
就是哭而已
Just crying.
有些人天生就是不快樂
Some people aren't built happy, you know.
天啊
Oh, my gosh.
我們把芝士吃完了
We ate all the cheese.
沒事的  芝士這么多  有大有小
It's okay. Lots of cheese vary in size.
-這就是一小塊  -真的好小
- This one was a small one. - It's so small.
-小小的  -這不是我們的錯
- It was tiny. - That's not our fault.
不然我們能怎么辦
What-what were we to do?
管它呢  我們去舞會吧
Fuck it! Let's just go to prom.
你媽媽應該有裙子吧
Doesn't your mom have a dress?
實話實說  我裙子幾個月前就準備好了
Let's be honest. I've had a dress for months.
紫色的
It's purple.
-是嗎  -你會喜歡的
- It is? - Uh-hmm, you're really gonna like it.
-來看看  -好的
- Come and see it. - Okay.
穿裙子嘍  扮漂亮嘍
Cracker time. Dress time.
希望它合身
I hope it fits.
小電影里  人們叫得可歡實了
People make so much noise in the movies,
但其實叫床不重要
but it's really not a big thing.
你完全可以全程安靜的
You can totally be quiet during it.
很神奇嗎
Was it amazing though?
我曾經是那么想要
I wanted it so badly,
但等真正經歷過之后
but then I found that when it happened...
我其實更喜歡干磨蹭
I-I really like dry humping much more.
你不是處女
You're not a virgin.
-我等不及去加州大集市了  -我知道
- I can't wait for state fair. - Ah, I know.
-水中過山車  -水中過山車
- Log ride. - Log ride.
-該死  -怎么了
- Shit. - What?
這個夏天  整個夏天  我都不在這
I'm not gonna be here this summer, like, all summer, basically.
-為什么不在  -我爸  我親爸
- Why not? - My dad, my real dad,
他在黃石公園重新出現了
he resurfaced in yellowstone,
他想讓我在去薩克拉門托市大學前
and he wants me to come there for the summer,
去他那里過暑假
before I start SCC.
我不會去別的地方讀大學
I'm not going anywhere to college,
感覺這是個去玩的好機會
so it seemed like a good opportunity.
是啊
Yeah.
我會很想你的
I'm gonna miss the fuck out of you.
我可能沒被錄取
I probably won't get in, so
那我就去戴維斯分校  天天都能見你
I'll go to Davis and I'll see you every day.
我再沒有魔法迷人  再沒有精靈為我奔走
Now, I want spirits to enforce, and art to enchant,
我的結局將要變成不幸的絕望
and my ending is despair.
除非依靠著萬能的祈禱的力量
Unless I be relieved by prayer,
它能把慈悲的神明的心中刺徹
which pierces so that it assaults mercy itself
赦免了可憐的下民的一切過失
and freeze all faults.
你們有罪過希望別人不在追究
As you from crimes would pardon thee.
愿你們也格外寬大  給我以自由
Let your indulgence set me free.
克里斯汀·"淑女鳥"·麥克弗森
Christine "Lady Bird" McPherson.
干杯
Cheers.
敬米格爾和他的新工作
To Miguel and his new job.
來  來
Here, here. Yes.
-敬淑女鳥去戴維斯分校  -敬戴維斯分校
- To Lady Bird going to Davis. - To Davis.
-恭喜  -不錯的學校
- Congratulations. - Good school.
我和我經理談過了
So I talked to my manager and,
你可以接著做我以前的工作
you could totally take over my old job.
好啊  謝謝你  米格爾
Great. Thanks, Miguel.
我真為你驕傲  淑女鳥
I'm so proud of you, Lady Bird.
你在臺上走得有點怪  但你走完了
You walked weird across the stage, but you did it!
-我走得不怪  -看上去有點怪
- I didn't walk weird. - Well, it seemed a little weird.
我想你們了
I missed you guys.
你知道候補名單的結果了嗎
Did you find out about the wait list?
該死
Fuck.
什么
What?
我都還沒被錄取  所以這可能根本不是問題
I'm not even in yet, so this might not even be a problem.
對不起  我不該瞞著你
I'm sorry. I shouldn't have gone behind your back.
我只是  我還不一定會去紐約呢
I just-- it's not like I'm definitely going to New York.
媽媽
Mom.
我就差一點被錄取
Aren't you, sort of,
你難道一點都不為我驕傲嗎
proud that I'm so close to getting in?
哪怕只是一點點
Just a little?
沒錯  我知道可能今年相對容易些
I mean... Yes, I know it was probably easier
因為911恐怖襲擊  申請人數要少一些
because 9-11 and less people applying with terrorism and all that,
可是...  對不起
but still though, I'm sorry.
我知道我有時會撒謊  不是個好人  可是
I know I can lie and not be a good person, but...
求你了  媽媽
Please, mom.
求你了  我真的很抱歉
Please. I'm so sorry.
我不是故意要傷害你的
I didn't mean to hurt you.
我感謝你為我所做的一切
I-I appreciate everything you've done for me.
我太忘恩負義了  實在對不起
I'm ungrateful and I'm so sorry.
真對不起  我以前想要的太多了
I'm so sorry I wanted more.
你就  求你了
Just... please!
別不理我
Talk to me.
我知道是我不好
I know I'm-I'm so bad!
我知道
I know I am.
但是求你了媽媽  別不理我
But please just talk to me, mom.
媽媽  求你跟我說句話吧
Mom, please talk to me.
這兒
Here.
然后下一個
Then next one.
一共三美元
That'll be three dollars.
你通過了
You passed.
-真的嗎  -是的
- Seriously? - Yes.
謝謝你
Thanks.
沒什么可謝的
It's not a thanking situation.
你要么通過  要么通不過
You either pass or you don't pass.
司機學員
進來
Come in.
*生日快樂*
*Happy birthday to you*
你還記得
You remembered.
你是我唯一的女兒
You're my only daughter.
好吧   謝麗也算是
Well, Shelly too. Kind of.
謝謝你
Thanks.
許個愿吧
Make a wish.
你和媽媽會因為這事離婚嗎
Are you and mom gonna get a divorce over this?
不會  我們負擔不起
No. We can't afford to.
爸
Dad.
我開玩笑的  不會
I'm kidding, no.
我愛你媽媽
I love your mom.
媽媽恨我嗎
Does mom hate me?
你們倆個性都太要強
You both have such strong personalities.
她不知道怎么才能幫到你  所以才沮喪
She doesn't know how to help you and it frustrates her.
我希望她能跟我說句話
I wish she'd talk to me.
她會的  我知道
She will. I know.
18歲快樂
Happy 18.
謝謝你
Thanks.
你想來點嗎
Do you want some?
好啊
Yes.
我要一包駱駝
One pack of Camel Lights please,
一張刮刮樂
and a scratcher,
一本《花花女郎》
and a Playgirl.
身份證
ID.
一共10.87美元
That'll be 10.87.
對了  今天是我生日
Oh, um, it's my birthday today.
我18歲了  所以可以買這些東西
I'm 18, which is why all these things, I can buy them.
這樣啊  生日快樂
Okay. Happy birthday.
謝謝
Thanks.
黃金國儲蓄銀行
用上她的獎學金
With her scholarships
我們再為房子重新貸下款  看還差多少
and then if we refinance the house, then where are we?
你只能在緊急情況下用
You're only supposed to use it for emergencies.
這是我的追蹤器
It's my tracking device.
03年畢業舞會  永恒之火
-謝謝你開車送我  -不客氣
- Thank you for driving. - You're welcome.
你不來嗎
You're not coming?
反正現在有安檢了  我沒法陪你走到登機口
You can't walk up to the gates anymore, anyway.
那倒是  可是我要去上大學了呀
Yeah, but I'm going to college.
你爸會送你到安檢那兒
Well, dad will walk you to security.
這里停車太貴了
Parking's too expensive here.
A航站樓  出發/值機
到了
There it is.
我來了
Hello.
沒事的
It's okay.
她會回來的
She'll be back.
She'll come back.
親愛的淑女鳥  我懷上你真是個奇跡  當時我已將近四十二歲
看著你長大是我今生最棒的冒險
親愛的克里斯汀  我知道你現在叫淑女鳥了  很好聽
但我想起我的奇跡你剛出生時我給你取的名字
親愛的淑女鳥  我每次看你都覺得你棒極了
她擔心自己
She was worried that
會寫錯字之類的
there would be errors or mistakes or something,
這樣你就會說她不會寫作
that you'd judge her writing abilities.
不會的
I wouldn't do that.
我覺得你應該讀到這些信
I thought you should have them,
我想讓你知道她有多愛你
but I want you to know how much she loves you,
但別告訴她我把信搶救出來了  好嗎
but also don't tell her I salvaged them, okay?
好的
Okay.
你相信上帝嗎
Do you believe in god?
-不信  -為什么呢
- No. - Why not?
你是認真的嗎  上帝這事很荒唐
Really? Uh, it's ridiculous.
人們互相叫著
People call each other by names
父母為他們取的名字
that their parents made up for them,
卻不相信上帝
but they won't believe in god.
你叫什么名字
What's your name?
克里斯汀  我叫克里斯汀
Christine. My name is Christine.
我叫大衛
I'm David.
你竟然握手
You shake.
-是啊  -好吧
- I shake. - Okay.
-你是哪里人  -薩克拉門托
- Where you from? - Sacramento.
不好意思  哪里
Sorry. Where?
舊金山
San Francisco.
酷啊  舊金山地方不錯
Oh, cool. Yeah. San Francisco's a great city.
我說真的
Really.
布魯斯  布魯斯
Bruce. Bruce.
錯了  我叫大衛
No. My name is David.
天哪  你這些音樂可真夠爛的
Jesus Christ. You have really bad music.
都是最熱門的曲子
It's all greatest hits.
可它們就是最熱門的
But they're the greatest.
熱門有什么錯嗎
What's wrong with that?
天哪
Oh, god!
對不起
I'm sorry.
你要我們做什么  她喝醉了
What do you want us to do? She's drunk.
克里斯汀·麥克弗森  血型A
不好意思  今天星期幾
Excuse me. What day is it?
禮拜日
Sunday.
謝謝你
Thank you.
這是麥克弗森家
You've reached the McPherson family.
請留言  謝謝
Please leave a message. Thank you.
媽媽  爸爸
Hi, mom and dad.
是我  克里斯汀
It's me. Christine.
你們為我取的名字  很好聽
It's the name you gave me. It's a good one.
爸爸  這通電話主要是給媽媽的
Dad, this is more for mom.
媽媽
Hey, mom.
你第一次在薩克拉門托開車時
Did you feel emotional the first time
你激動嗎
that you drove in Sacramento?
我很激動  而且我很想告訴你
I did, and I wanted to tell you,
可惜那時我們不說話
but we weren't really talking when it happened.
我熟悉的每一處轉彎
All those bends I've known my whole life,
每一家商店
and stores
以及所有一切
and the whole thing.
但我想告訴你
But I wanted to tell you...
我愛你
I love you.
謝謝你  我...
Thank you. I'm...
謝謝你
Thank you.